Guide to the Eva J. Salber Papers, 1937-1990
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Duke University Medical Center, 1965-1990, undated
  A variety of material relating primarily to the Community Health Models Unit and the Health Facilitators Project. Included are survey forms, charts and graphs, texts of lectures, budgets, project outlines, field reports, a few writings by Salber, and other materials. Also includes correspondence, typed transcripts of interviews, charts and graphs, snapshots, questionnaire forms, training manuals, newsletters, announcements, clippings, notes, reports, and meeting minutes. Explanatory notes added later by Salber can be found throughout.
  Arranged chronologically, then alphabetically by type of material within two subseries, Community Health Education Program and Department of Community and Family Medicine. Dates may overlap where folders created by Salber are kept intact.
  - Community Health Education Program (CHEP)
    - 1965-1976 (Box 23)
    - CHEP News, 1976 (Box 23)
    - Clippings, 1973-1977, undated, (2 folders) (Box 23)
    - Correspondence, 1973-1976, (2 folders) (Box 23)
    - Meeting announcements for Bragtown and Rougemont/Bahama Health Advisory Boards, 1973-1977 (Box 24)
    - Meetings, notes, with various groups, 1972-1977 (Box 24)
    - Minutes, 1974-1976, (4 folders) (Box 24)
    - Minutes of the Combined Rougemont/Bahama and Bragtown Health Advisory Boards with CHEP Health Education Planning Committee, 1972-1976, (2 folders) (Box 24)
    - Training Program for Health Facilitators, 1974-1976 (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous, 1975-1976 (Box 25)
  - Department of Community and Family Medicine
    - Community Health Models Unit:
      - 1970-1984, (4 folders) (Box 25)
      - Community profiles of Rougemont/Bahama and Bragtown, undated (Box 25)
      - Field observations, 1972-1974, (2 folders) (Box 25)
      - Health Interview Survey, 1970-1976, (2 folders) (Box 25)
      - History, 1970-1975 (Box 26)
      - Missions and goals, 1974-1985 (Box 26)
      - Reminiscences,1972 (Box 26)
      - Reports, 1972-1973 (Box 26)
      - Miscellaneous, 1976-1981, (2 folders) (Box 26)
    - Directory,1979 (Box 26)
    - Health Facilitator Program:
      - 1974 (Box 26)
      - Correspondence, 1979-1990 (Box 26)
      - Facilitator interviews, 1975-1990, (2 folders) (Box 26)
      - Network analysis to identify health facilitators, undated (Box 27)
      - Notebook, 1974-1976 (Box 27)
      - One-year follow-up, 1977-1978, (2 folders) (Box 27)
      - Pictures, undated (Box 27)
      - Problem/Advice sheets, 1974-1975, (2 folders) (Box 27)
      - Requests for information and assistance,1979 (Box 28)
      - Training, undated (Box 28)
      - Miscellaneous:
        - 1974-1986, undated (Box 28)
        - Forms,1976 (Box 28)
- Health Facilitator Program Outgrowths, 1976-1990, undated
  Chiefly printed material, reports, grant proposals, project summaries, training materials, and program evaluations. Also includes correspondence, agendas, meeting minutes, financial reports, outlines of programs, and questionnaire forms. Most information is related to the North Carolina Baptist State Convention. Explanatory notes added later by Salber can be found throughout.
  Arranged alphabetically. Dates may overlap where folders created by Salber are kept intact.
  - Community Health Education, South Africa, 1977-1978 (Box 28)
  - General Baptist State Convention of North Carolina, Health and Human Services Program, 1976-1986, undated, (4 folders) (Box 28)
  - General Baptist State Convention of North Carolina, Health and Human Services Program, undated (Box 29)
    - Annual report,1986 (Box 29)
    - Report, undated (Box 29)
  - Health teams: Bolivar, Tenn., 1975-1977, undated (Box 29)
  - Housing Facilitator Program, 1976-1979, undated, (2 folders) (Box 29)
  - Lumbee Regional Development Association, 1981-1990 (Box 30)
  - Migrant Lay Health Advisors, 1988-1989, (2 folders) (Box 30)
  - Natural Helpers and Helping Mothers Program, 1986-1990 (Box 30)
  - Senior Advocate Volunteer Program, 1977-1978 (Box 30)
- Student Files, 1970-1990, undated
  Correspondence between Salber and students or about students, recommendation letters, student evaluation forms, course evaluations, students' written and research work, curriculum vitae, class rolls, grant and fellowship proposals, copies of application forms, and a small amount of printed material. Explanatory notes added later by Salber can be found throughout the series.
  Arranged alphabetically by students' last names.
  This series is restricted.
  - Ainsworth, Richard, 1973 (Box 30)
  - Allcott, John, 1987-1988 (Box 30)
  - Angle, Marcia, 1979-1990 (Box 30)
  - Avorn, Jerry, 1970 (Box 30)
  - Chapman, Jean, undated (Box 30)
  - Chatterton, Howard, 1974 (Box 30)
  - Chin, Linda, 1978-1979 (Box 30)
  - Clardy, Betsy, 1979-1980 (Box 31)
  - Dennis, Betty, 1976-1979 (Box 31)
  - DiCarlo, Elizabeth, 1986 (Box 31)
  - Doyle, Dan, 1988-1989 (Box 31)
  - Dykes, Jim, 1978-1979 (Box 31)
  - Eden, Scott, 1978-1979 (Box 31)
  - Epstein, Arnold, 1975-1978 (Box 31)
  - Fitch, Nancy, 1978-1983 (Box 31)
  - Hanson, Laura, 1983-1988 (Box 31)
  - Henderson-James, Douglas and Judith R. Karelitz, 1978? (Box 31)
  - Henley, Michele, 1981 (Box 31)
  - Levine, Stuart, 1982 (Box 31)
  - Manning, John, 1976-1977 (Box 31)
  - Matthews, Dale, 1979 (Box 31)
  - Maxwell, Richard B., 1975 (Box 31)
  - Miller, Ed, 1978 (Box 32)
  - Milliken, Nancy, 1979-1989 (Box 32)
  - Raney, Curtis, 1978 (Box 32)
  - Shaw, Robert, 1975 (Box 32)
  - Silimperi, Diana, 1978-1981, (2 folders) (Box 32)
  - Stahl, Christiane, 1977-1983, (2 folders) (Box 32)
  - Tipermas, Alan, 1979-1981 (Box 32)
  - Vilinsky, Debbie, 1978 (Box 32)
  - Washburn, Ronald, 1978 (Box 32)
  - Weiner, Alan, 1985-1989 (Box 32)
  - Weir, Sam and Chad Stevens, 1980 (Box 33)
  - Williamson, Deborah, 1978 (Box 33)
  - Wisson, Larry, 1977-1989 (Box 33)
  - Worthy, Paula, undated (Box 33)
  - Medical students, 1969-1990, undated (Box 33)
  - Student award nominations,1979 (Box 33)
- Conferences and consultations, 1969-1988.
  Correspondence, printed programs, reports, texts of Salber's speeches, including writings delivered at conferences, notes for speeches, program outlines and schedules, charts, copies of articles, project descriptions and updates; and to a lesser extent, committee reports, minutes, a grant proposal, and contracts for Salber's consulting work. Explanatory notes added later by Salber can be found throughout.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Arizona and Vancouver Conferences: Community Perspectives, the Lay Advisor Approach, 1983-1984 (Box 33)
  - Canadian College and Health Service Executives and King's Fund College Course, Ottawa University, 1974, Mar. (Box 33)
  - Center for Health Administration Studies, University of Chicago; Self-care Practices of the United States Population,1979 (Box 33)
  - Duke School of Nursing Alumni Association, Second Annual Synopsium, Trends in Health Care Delivery,1974 (Box 33)
  - Family Medicine Conference, 1979-1981 (Box 33)
  - General Baptist State Convention of North Carolina; Health Facilitator Concept, 1979-1980 (Box 33)
  - Health Care in the Developing World: Miscellaneous, 1979-1984 (Box 33)
  - Health Education Workshop (Paoli, Indiana), 1978, Apr. (Box 33)
  - Johnson and Johnson: Development of Family Liaison Health Facilitator for New Brunswick Public Schools, 1977-1979 (Box 33)
  - Montefiore Conference on Community Health Promotion and the Hospital: The Role of Lay People as Health Facilitators, 1978-1979 (Box 33)
  - National Center for Health Services Research Conference on Consumer Self-care in Health,1976 (Box 34)
  - National Center for Health Statistics Conference; Panel Meeting on Minority Statistics, 1974-1980 (Box 34)
  - North Carolina Student Rural Health Coalition Advisory Board, 1978-1983, (2 folders) (Box 34)
  - Swaziland: Water and Sanitation for Health (WASH) Project, 1979-1984 (Box 34)
  - Urban Affairs Colloquium: Informal Support Systems,1979 (Box 34)
  - Miscellaneous, 1969-1988, (2 folders) (Box 34)
- Teaching Files, 1967-1989, undated
  Index cards containing Salber's lecture notes, texts of lectures, copies of class handouts, and course outlines. Also includes handwritten notes, course evaluations, reprints of articles, student evaluation forms, and correspondence.
  - Course offerings,1973, undated (Box 35)
  - Duke University Medical Center: Notes for medical student orientation and course evaluations by students, 1978-1982 (Box 35)
  - Lecture notes, 1973-1982, (3 folders) (Box 35)
  - Lecture schedule and notes while at the Martha Eliot Center, 1967-1970 (Box 35)
  - Lectures: Miscellaneous, 1969-1970 (Box 35)
  - Notes for Duke University Medical Center course “Ethics and Human Values,” 1988-1989 (Box 35)
  - Student evaluations of Salber courses, 1981-1982 (Box 35)
  - Miscellaneous,1975 (Box 35)
- Project files, 1959-1986.
  Correspondence to and from Salber, reports, studies, copies of articles, application forms, proposals, abstracts of research projects, survey forms, background material for research, tables and graphs, and texts of speeches, chiefly relating to smoking research. Includes explanatory notes added later by Salber.
  Arranged alphabetically by research subjects of Salber and others.
  - International study of breast cancer and lactation,1969 (Box 36)
  - Northern Fairview, Orange County, N.C., 1977-1979 (Box 36)
  - Rural Health: University of Virginia School of Nursing, 1981-1986 (Box 36)
  - Smoking research:
    - Anti-smoking campaigns,1967 (Box 36)
    - Clippings, 1961-1964 (Box 36)
    - Conference on smoking,1971 (Box 36)
    - Follow-up study on Newton school children, 1959-1965 (Box 36)
    - Forms and instructions, 1962? (Box 36)
    - Questionnaires,1959 (Box 36)
    - Reports, 1960-1963 (Box 36)
    - Tables and graphs,1959 (Box 36)
    - Writings and speeches, 1964-1968, (2 folders) (Box 36)
- Pictures series, 1979-1980 and undated
  Chiefly black and white photographs taken by Dominic D'Eustachio, who created the illustrations for Don't Send Me Flowers When I'm Dead. Many of the photographs in this series were presumably taken for the book. A number of them contain notes on the subject added by the photographer; some are mounted. Also includes a few contact prints. Most material is undated. Larger photographs are housed in flat boxes with the collection.
  - 1979-1980, undated, (6 folders) (Box 37)
  - South Africa, undated (Box 37)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 38)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 39)
- Miscellaneous series, 1938-1990, undated
  Includes letters of commendation and recommendation for Salber, awards, correspondence, typed reports and studies, grant proposals, meeting minutes, printed material, drafts of Salber's writings, a transcript of an interview with Salber, and biographical information about Salber, most written for a variety of biographical dictionary publications.
  Arranged chronologically and alphabetically by subject or type of material.
  - 1964-1990, undated (Box 40)
  - Background material on Durham, 1968-1981 (Box 40)
  - Biographical information, 1969-1989, undated, (2 folders) (Box 40)
  - British American Festival, 1983-1984 (Box 40)
  - Bromley-Heath Tenant Management Corporation:
    - 1981-1989 (Box 40)
    - Clippings, 1971-1981 (Box 40)
  - Center for Community Health and Medical Care, 1969-1971 (Box 40)
  - Clippings, 1969-1989, undated (Box 40)
  - Community participation in health care
    - 1969-1970 (Box 40)
    - Harvard Medical School, 1968-1970 (Box 40)
  - Family care homes and homes for the aged directory, 1974-1976 (Box 41)
  - Fogarty Fellowship, 1979-1984, undated (Box 41)
  - Interview with Salber, undated (Box 41)
  - Jamaica Plain Area Planning Action Council, 1967-1969, (3 folders) (Box 41)
  - Jamaica Plain Area Planning Action Council, 1967-1969 (Box 42)
  - Jamaica Plain Wide Health Coordinating Committee, 1969-1970 (Box 42)
  - Questionnaire: Radcliffe College, Mary Ingraham Bunting Institute, 1965-1989 (Box 42)
  - Salber reminiscences,1990, undated (Box 42)
  - Testimonials, awards, 1938-1990, undated (Box 42)
- Oversize Materials
  - Writings and Speeches Series (Opaperfolder Folders 1-2)
    - 1983-1989, undated, (2 folders) (Opaperfolder Folders 1-2)
  - Martha M. Eliot Family Health Center Series (Box 43)
    - Scrapbook, 1967-1969 (Box 43)
  - Duke University Medical Center Series (Opaperfolder Folders 1-2)
    - Community Health Education Program, 1973-1975 (Opaperfolder Folders 1-2)
  - Health Facilitator Program--Outgrowths Series (Opaperfolder Folders 1-2)
    - undated (Opaperfolder Folders 1-2)
  - Student Files Series (Opaperfolder Folders 1-2)
    - 1973, undated (Opaperfolder Folders 1-2)
  - Project Files Series (Opaperfolder Folders 1-2)
    - 1977-1979, undated (Opaperfolder Folders 1-2)
  - Miscellaneous Series (Opaperfolder Folders 1-2)
    - 1968-1989, (2 folders) (Opaperfolder Folders 1-2)